window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Engineering_Mathematics - Linear_Algebra — Slot 6 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Linear_Algebra — Slot 6",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Let A be an \\(n \\times n\\) matrix of the following form.<br>\n\\(A = \\begin{bmatrix}3&amp;1&amp;0&amp;0&amp;0&amp;\\ldots&amp;0&amp;0&amp;0\\\\ 1&amp;3&amp;1&amp;0&amp;0&amp;\\ldots&amp;0&amp;0&amp;0\\\\ 0&amp;1&amp;3&amp;1&amp;0&amp;\\ldots&amp;0&amp;0&amp;0\\\\ 0&amp;0&amp;1&amp;3&amp;1&amp;\\ldots&amp;0&amp;0&amp;0\\\\ \\ldots\\\\ \\ldots \\\\ 0&amp;0&amp;0&amp;0&amp;0&amp;\\ldots&amp;1&amp;3&amp;1\\\\ 0&amp;0&amp;0&amp;0&amp;0&amp;\\ldots&amp;0&amp;1&amp;3\\\\ \\end{bmatrix}_{n\\times n}\\)<br>\nWhat is the value of the determinant of A? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\frac{5+\\sqrt3}{2}\\right)^{n-1} \\left(\\frac{5\\sqrt3 + 7}{2 \\sqrt 3}\\right) +\\left(\\frac{5-\\sqrt3}{2}\\right)^{n-1} \\left(\\frac{5\\sqrt3 - 7}{2 \\sqrt 3}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\frac{7+\\sqrt5}{2}\\right)^{n-1} \\left(\\frac{7\\sqrt5 + 3}{2 \\sqrt 5}\\right) +\\left(\\frac{7-\\sqrt5}{2}\\right)^{n-1} \\left(\\frac{7\\sqrt5 - 3}{2 \\sqrt 5}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\frac{3+\\sqrt7}{2}\\right)^{n-1} \\left(\\frac{3\\sqrt7 + 5}{2 \\sqrt 7}\\right) +\\left(\\frac{3-\\sqrt7}{2}\\right)^{n-1} \\left(\\frac{3\\sqrt7 - 5}{2 \\sqrt 7}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\frac{3+\\sqrt5}{2}\\right)^{n-1} \\left(\\frac{3\\sqrt5 + 7}{2 \\sqrt 5}\\right) + \\left(\\frac{3-\\sqrt5}{2}\\right)^{n-1} \\left(\\frac{3\\sqrt5 - 7}{2 \\sqrt 5}\\right)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\frac{3+\\sqrt5}{2}\\right)^{n-1} \\left(\\frac{3\\sqrt5 + 7}{2 \\sqrt 5}\\right) + \\left(\\frac{3-\\sqrt5}{2}\\right)^{n-1} \\left(\\frac{3\\sqrt5 - 7}{2 \\sqrt 5}\\right)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3675/gate2004-it-32\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>What values of x, y and z satisfy the following system of linear equations?<br>\n\\(\\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp;2 &amp;3 \\\\ 1&amp; 3 &amp;4 \\\\ 2&amp; 2 &amp;3 \\end{bmatrix} \\begin{bmatrix} x\\\\y \\\\ z \\end{bmatrix} = \\begin{bmatrix} 6\\\\8 \\\\ 12 \\end{bmatrix}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>x = 6, y = 3, z = 2</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>x = 12, y = 3, z = - 4</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>x = 6, y = 6, z = - 4</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>x = 12, y = - 3, z = 0</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>x = 6, y = 6, z = - 4</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3647/gate2004-it-6\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>In an M x N matrix such that all non-zero entries are covered in a rows and b columns. Then the\nmaximum number of non-zero entries, such that no two are on the same row or column, is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\leq\\) a+b</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\leq\\) max{a,b}</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\leq\\) min{M-a,N-b}</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\leq\\) min{a,b}</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\leq\\) min{a,b}</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1070/gate2004-76#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>How many solutions does the following system of linear equations have?<br><br>\n-x + 5y = -1 <br>\nx - y = 2 <br>\nx + 3y = 3 <br> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>infinitely many</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>two distinct solutions</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>unique</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>none</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>unique</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1065/gate2004-71#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Let A,B,C,D be n x n matrices, each with non-zero determinant. If ABCD=I, then \\(B^{-1}\\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(D^{-1}C^{-1}A^{-1}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>CDA</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>ADC</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Does not necessarily exist</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>CDA</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1024/gate2004-27#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>The number of different n x n symmetric matrices with each element being either 0 or 1 is : (Note:\npower (2,x) is same as \\(2^{x}\\)) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>power (2,n)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>power (2,\\(n^{2}\\))</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>power (2,\\((n^{2}+n)/2\\))</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>power (2,\\((n^{2}-n)/2\\))</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>power (2,\\((n^{2}+n)/2\\))</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1023/gate2004-26#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following system of linear equations <br>  \\(\\begin{bmatrix} 2 &amp; 1 &amp; -4\\\\ 4 &amp; 3 &amp; -12\\\\ 1 &amp; 2 &amp; -8 \\end{bmatrix}\\begin{bmatrix} x\\\\ y\\\\ z \\end{bmatrix}\\begin{bmatrix} \\alpha \\\\ 5\\\\ 7 \\end{bmatrix}\\) <br>  Notice that the second and the third columns of the coefficient matrix are linearly\ndependent. For how many values of \\(\\alpha\\), does this system of equations have\ninfinitely many solutions? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2003)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>infinitely many</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/932/gate2003-41#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>The rank of the matrix \\(\\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp; 1\\\\ 0&amp; 0 \\end{bmatrix}\\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2002)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>4</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>0</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/805/gate2002-1-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>A polynomial p(x) satisfies the following:<br>\np(1) = p(3) = p(5) = 1 <br>\np(2) = p(4) = -1<br>\nThe minimum degree of such a polynomial is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2000)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>4</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>4</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/651/gate2000-2-4\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>The determinant of the matrix<br>\\(\\begin{bmatrix}2 &amp;0 &amp;0 &amp;0 \\\\ 8&amp; 1&amp; 7&amp; 2\\\\ 2&amp; 0&amp;2 &amp;0 \\\\ 9&amp;0 &amp; 6 &amp; 1 \\end{bmatrix}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2000)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>4</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>0</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>15</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>20</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>4</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/626/gate2000-1-3\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following determinant \\(\\Delta = \\begin{vmatrix} 1 &amp; a &amp; bc \\\\ 1 &amp; b &amp; ca \\\\ 1 &amp; c &amp; ab \\end{vmatrix}\\)<br>\nWhich of the following is a factor of \\(\\Delta\\)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>a+b</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>a-b</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>a+b+c</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>abc</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>a-b</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1674/gate1998-2-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>The rank of the matrix given below is:<br>\n\\(\\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp;4 &amp;8 &amp;7\\\\ 0 &amp;0&amp; 3 &amp;0\\\\ 4 &amp;2&amp; 3 &amp;1\\\\ 3 &amp;12 &amp;24 &amp;21 \\end{bmatrix}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>4</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>3</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1673/gate1998-2-1\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following set of equations<br>\n\\(x+2y=5\\\\ 4x+8y=12\\\\ 3x+6y+3z=15\\)<br>\nThis set <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>has unique solution</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>has no solution</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>has finite number of solutions</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>has infinite number of solutions</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>has no solution</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1639/gate1998-1-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>A polynomial p(x) is such that p(0)=5,p(1)=4,p(2)=9 and p(3)=20. The minimum degree it should have is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>4</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>2</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2245/gate1997-4-4\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(A=(a_{ij})\\) be an n-rowed square matrix and \\(I_{12}\\) be the matrix obtained by interchanging the first and second rows of the n-rowed Identity matrix. Then \\(AI_{12}\\) is such that its first <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Row is the same as its second row</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Row is the same as the second row of A</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Column is the same as the second column of A</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Row is all zero</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Column is the same as the second column of A</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2243/gate1997-4-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
